Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Bertram Metter Papers, 1908-2000 and undated, bulk 1953-1989 RL.00730
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Bertram Metter papers
1908-2000 and undated, bulk 1953-1989
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company
RL.00730
8.7 Linear Feet
Bertram Metter worked for over thirty years as an advertising and marketing executive, most notably as a copywriter, creative director, and Vice Chairman at J. Walter Thompson USA (JWT). In in early years at JWT, Metter worked as a direct response specialist for the Ford Motor Company direct marketing operation. He also served as a primary on the Ford account, during which time he directed print and television promotion for Ford and played a key role in the launching of several new car models. The Bertram Metter Papers span 1908 to 2000, with the bulk of the collection dating 1953 through the late 1980s. Collection contains materials in a variety of formats, including correspondence, writings, newspaper and magazine clippings, sheet music, printed materials, photographs, and photostats. In addition to materials for the Ford Motor Company, the collection documents Metter's work for other major clients, including the Pepsi-Cola Company (Mexico) and Liggett & Myers Tobacco Company. Bulk of the collection consists of advertising and marketing research, client reports and correspondence, promotional materials, and other professional files. Also contains materials related to Metter's later work as a consultant and author, including drafts of an unpublished book manuscript entitled Breaking the Rules at J. Walter Thompson, a chronicle of his career at JWT.
3250 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Bertram Metter Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer in 1987.
Additions were received in 2003.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1927 Aug. 14 Born in New York, NY
1949 B.A. Brooklyn College
1952 M.A. Columbia University
1953-1956 Copy chief, New York Mirror, Advertising Promotion Department
1956-1959 Copy chief, Newsweek Magazine (New York), Circulation Department
1960-1991 Joined the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT), New York; initially hired as a direct response specialist in charge of the Ford direct mail operation
1965-1973 Vice President, JWT
1969 Creative Supervisor, JWT
1973-1978 Senior Vice President, JWT
1974 Creative Director, JWT
1978 Became Executive Vice President, JWT
1980 Received A.M.P., Harvard University (Advanced Management Program, Harvard Business School)
1980 Board of Directors, JWT USA
1982 Executive Creative Director, JWT USA
1984 Vice Chairman, JWT USA
1986-1987 Chairman, Board of Directors, JWT USA
1987 Became advertising and marketing consultant, primarily to the Ross Roy Group ( Bloomfield Hills, MI) Resigned from JWT USA
1988 Rehired as Chairman, Board of Directors, JWT USA after the company was bought by WPP Group, plc ( Great Britain)
1991 Retired from JWT
1991- Ongoing consultant to JWT
After Burton J. Manning, Metter became only the second creative director at JWT to rise to the level of Chairman, Board of Directors. In the midst of a management crisis that hit the financially ailing company, Metter resigned in 1987. Metter was rehired as Chairman in 1988; his primary tasks were to coordinate new business efforts for JWT USA, provide additional strategic advice for ongoing accounts, and focus on general management and creative troubleshooting.
During his time with JWT, Metter won numerous creative awards, including Clios, Cannes Film Festival awards, Advertising Age 100 Best TV Commercials, and others. He published several articles about the advertising business in Advertising Age and other industry publications.
Collection Overview
The Bertram Metter Papers span 1908 to 2000, with the bulk of the collection dating 1953 through the late 1980s. The collection includes materials in a variety of formats, including correspondence, writings, newspaper and magazine clippings, sheet music, printed materials, photographs, and photostats, that document Metter's thirty years in advertising and marketing, with a focus on his career as a copywriter, creative director, and Vice Chairman at J. Walter Thompson USA (JWT). The collection provides a record of Metter's early work as a direct response specialist for the Ford Motor Company direct marketing operation, and other roles on the Ford account (Metter directed print and television promotion for Ford and played a key role in the launching of several new car models). In addition to Ford materials, the collection documents Metter's work for other major clients, including the Pepsi-Cola Company (Mexico) and Liggett & Myers Tobacco Company. While the bulk of the collection consists of advertising and marketing research, client reports and correspondence, promotional materials, and other professional files, the collection also contains materials related to Metter's later work as a consultant and author, including drafts of an unpublished book manuscript entitled Breaking the Rules at J. Walter Thompson, a chronicle of his career at JWT.
The collection is organized into four series: Professional Files, Writings, Ford Motor Company Account Files, and Other Clients.
The Professional Files Series contains JWT office (non-client) files, memoranda, and publications; industry publications and press clippings; overviews of Metter's professional biography; and limited files on Metter's consulting work for Ross Roy Advertising. The Writings Series contains Metter's writings on the advertising industry; bulk of series is composed of an unpublished book manuscript entitled Breaking the Rules at J. Walter Thompson, comprised primarily of chapter drafts and research. The Ford Series, the largest series in the collection, includes materials relating to the launch and promotion of new models (Escort, Maverick, Mustang, Olympic, Pinto, Thunderbird, and Torino); marketing research and strategic reports; Ford direct mail materials and newsletters; television commercial scripts and storyboards; advertisement clippings and headlines; reproduction prints of early photographs of the Model T from the Ford Archives, Henry Ford Museum; photostats promoting the Ford Erika; and photocopies of sheet music of Ford songs from the early twentieth century. The Other Clients Series includes materials relating to general marketing research; new business acquisition; and promotional campaigns for clients other than Ford, including Firestone, Liggett & Myers, and Pepsi-Cola (Mexico). Large-format materials have been removed from their original series location and relocated to Oversize Materials.
Related Material
Other materials related to this collection may be found elsewhere in the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives, including: Account Files; Competitive Advertisements Collection; Domestic Advertisements Collection; Corporation Vertical Files; and Review Board Records.
Advertising -- Cigarettes; Advertising -- History; Advertising -- Automobiles -- United States; Advertising -- Brand name products; Clippings (information artifacts); Advertising -- United States; Photostats; Photographs; Copy writers -- United States; Marketing research -- United States; Advertising agencies -- United States; Sheet music; Advertising executives -- United States; Advertising -- Research; Advertising agencies -- Management; Ford Motor Company; Ford Motor Company -- Marketing; J. Walter Thompson Company; J. Walter Thompson Company; J. Walter Thompson Company. New York Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. North America; Metter, Bertram, 1927-; Pepsi-Cola Company -- Mexico; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Liggett & Myers Tobacco Company
- Professional Files Series, 1922-1990 and undated, bulk 1960-1990, 2 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains industry publications, press clippings, correspondence and memoranda, photographs, and non-client files relating to Metter's work at J. Walter Thompson and Ross Roy Advertising. Also includes materials documenting Metter's professional biography. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Industry publications (Box 1)
    - ad day/u.s.a (National Newsletter of Advertising and Marketing), 1983 Apr. (Box 1)
    - Advertising Age
      - Article: Top 100 Agencies By Gross Income, 1980-1987 (Box 1)
        Gross income of Ross Roy Advertising is highlighted in each table.
      - Clippings, 1966-1985 and undated (Box 1)
      - Issues: 1980 Sept. 1; 1988 Apr. 4; 1989 Nov. 27, 3 folders (Box 1)
        Includes leading article on WPP sale of Lord, Geller, Federico, Einstein: 'Conspiracy': Sorrell claims breakaway is a plot to force LGFE sale.
      - Supplements/Special issues
        - Twentieth Century Advertising and the Economy of Abundance: A Review of 50 Years of American Advertising, its Economic and Social Importance, and Its Contribution to the American Standard of Living, 1980 Apr. 30 (Box 1)
        - U.S. Advertising Agency Profiles: 1988 Edition, 1988 Mar. 30 (Box 1)
    - ADWEEK
      - Clippings, 1983-1990 (Box 1)
      - Issues, 1984-1989, 4 folders (Box 1)
        Includes Agency Report Card: Grading the Performances inserts for 1983 and 1984.
    - Automotive News, 1980 and 1983 (Box 1)
    - Back Stage: The complete service weekly for the commuications and entertainment industry, 1984 Oct. 19 (Box 1)
      Includes articles on Creative Directors in top management positions and Metter's appointment to Vice Chairman of JWT USA.
    - Credits: Current Advertising and Who Created It (Vol. 2, No. 4), 1984 Nov. (Box 1)
      Metter photo and brief essay, Future Advertising: Great Expectations, pages 8-9.
    - Forbes: Thoughts on the Business of Life, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
      Includes circled quote from Bertolt Brecht.
    - Grey Matter: Newsletter of Grey Advertising Inc. (Vol. 39, No. 4), 1968 Apr. (Box 1)
    - Madison Avenue, 1973 (Box 1)
      Includes article Building Believability into TV Commercials.
    - New York Magazine, 1982 Mar. and 1985 Apr. (Box 1)
      March 1982 issue includes article, The Strange Case of Marie Luisi, on JWT executive Luisi and financial scandals.
    - The New York Times--Various, 1985 and 1988 (Box 1)
      Includes articles on JWT Direct Network(direct marketing) and WPP takeover of Lord, Geller, Federico, Einstein in 1988.
    - Newsweek: Tuning Out TV Ads: Pepsi Pulls Its Too-Hot-To-Handle Madonna Spot... 1989 Apr. 17 (Box 1)
    - The Power Newsletter: Analysis, News, and Commentary on the Automotive Market, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
    - Printers' Ink: The Magazine of Advertising and Marketing Management, 1966 (Box 1)
      See page 41, Outstanding Ads--1965 Newspaper, Ford Campaign by J. Walter Thompson.
    - Shooting Commercials: Music page (Vol. 6, No. 5), 1983 May (Box 1)
      Contains blurb on Metter's son: J. Walter Thompson's creative director Bert Metter's son is a graduate of the Hart School of Music (Hartford Conservatory) and a professional musician.
    - Television/Radio Age, 1984 Sept. 17 (Box 1)
    - Werbe-Woche, 1985 Oct. (Box 1)
      German-language advertising and marketing journal.
  - J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT)
    - Advertising campaigns (JWT promotion)
      - Advertisement clippings, 1983, 1985 and undated (Box 1)
        Includes advertisements from The New York Times and Wall Street Journal: How come a big, conservative ad agency is creating America's most outstanding advertising? and Main Street ranks Madison Avenue.
      - Promotional materials (March 4th advertisement, JWT mailings/booklets), 1987 and undated (Box 1)
    - Brochures/Presentation Reports
      - A Brief Profile of J. Walter Thompson brochures
        - JWT New York, circa early 1980s (Box 1)
        - Prepared for Mr. Tony Cox (President HBO Network), 1983 June (Box 1)
        - Prepared for the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, circa 1980s (Box 1)
      - Conference brochures
        - JWT Through the Looking Glass (World Advertising Forum, Epcot), 1984 May (Box 1)
        - People You Are Meeting Today: JWT/Florida Grapefruit staff, undated (Box 1)
          Features photo insert of Metter as Executive VP.
      - Various
        - Consumer Panel: Strategic Services Report, 1987 (Box 1)
        - Creative Uprising, circa 1987 (Box 1)
        - Inside JWT: JWT London, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
        - J. Walter Thompson: A Legend in His Own Time presentation (Marion Howington, Senior VP), 1988 May 19 (Box 1)
        - Main Street Ranks Madison Avenue/ Annual Report of America's Leading Agencies, circa 1985-1986 (Box 1)
        - The New American Consumers: A Study of Dramatic Changes in the American Market, 1985 (Box 1)
        - A Special JWT Study: How Much Do Remote Control Devices Increase Flipping? (On television habits, channel flipping, and the future of television), 1985-1987 and undated (Box 1)
        - Survey of Advertising Professionals/American Marketing Awards, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence
      - Ford management presentation, 1979 and undated (Box 1)
      - Letters of congratulations--Metter apppointment to Vice Chairman, 1984 (Box 1)
      - Memoranda
        - Account Planning, 1987 and undated (Box 1)
        - From Don Johnston (Chairman), 1983 (Box 1)
          Memoranda on Ryder, Goodyear, and Hertz accounts.
        - From Burt Manning, 1982-1984 (Box 1)
          Memoranda on Toys R Us, HBO, and Ryder accounts.
        - From Metter
          - Advertising Age memo (with responses), 1986 Nov. (Box 1)
          - Ad Year in Review ad memo (with responses), 1986-1987 (Box 1)
          - Various, 1983-1986 (Box 1)
        - From Page Procter, 1960 (Box 1)
          On success of Ford direct mail.
        - Various, 1983-1988 (Box 1)
          Includes memoranda on Goodyear and Sears client accounts; also on JWT House Ad and Business Week article.
    - Drexel Burnham Lambert: Research abstracts (on WPP Group), 1988-1989 (Box 1)
    - Executive Career Documentation Binders (Henderson Files)
      - James Webb Young Documents Since 1922
        James Webb Young (1886-1973) was an advertising professor, consultant, and executive associated with JWT for over fifty years; he also served as Chairman of the War Advertising Council from 1945-1947 and advocated for its post-war transition to The Advertising Council.
        - Volume I: Clips, 1922-1968 and undated (Box 1)
        - Volume II: Personal letters, 1964-1974 and undated (Box 1)
          Includes biographical timeline detailing Webb's career.
      - Norman H. Strouse with JWT Clips After His Retirement, 1968, 1964-1977 (Box 1)
        Strouse served as the third CEO of JWT from 1960-1967, and Chairman of the Board from 1967 until his retirement in 1968, the culmination of over forty years at JWT.
    - Financial reports (Box 2)
      - Annual reports, 1979, 1985-1986, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - First Quarter Report, 1987 Mar. 31 (Box 2)
      - Operating Review (graphs, charts), 1987 and undated (Box 2)
    - Management/Administration files, 1987 and undated (Box 2)
    - New Business Department notes, undated (Box 2)
    - Newsletters
      - J. Walter Thompson Company News, 1966-1971 (Box 2)
      - J. Walter Thompson News, 1982-1985 (Box 2)
        Includes articles on Multinationality and Mexico; JWT Frankfurt/Pepsi; Dan Seymour (fourth president of JWT); Madison Avenue's Super Bowl.
      - Management News (internal circulation), 1984 Nov. (Box 2)
      - New York: J. Walter Thompson Company New York News, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
      - The New York Thompson (Vol. III, No. 3), 1980 May 1 (Box 2)
    - Press clippings (weekly memos), 1989 (Box 2)
      Compilations of articles from Advertising Age, ADWEEK, The Economist, The New York Times, and The Wall Street Journal; most notably, cover article from The New York Times Magazine, Brits Buy Up the Ad Business.
    - Press releases
      - Bert Metter Appointed Vice Chairman of J. Walter Thompson USA, 1984 Oct. 10 (Box 2)
      - Bert Metter Named Executive Creative Director At JWT, 1982 Mar. 22 (Box 2)
      - J. Walter Thompson Launches Working Scholarship Awards for Creative People, 1983 Mar. 30 (Box 2)
      - Two Directors Named At J. Walter Thompson Company (Metter and Steve Bowen appointments), 1985 May 9 (Box 2)
    - Stockholder materials
      - Letters to Stockholders--WPP tender offer, 1987 June (Box 2)
      - Notice of Annual Meeting of Stockholders, 1978-1979, 1983 (Box 2)
      - Owl Group/WPP tender offer, 1987 June 29 (Box 2)
      - Prospectus
        - 1969, 1973 and 1977 Stock Incentive Plans, 1977-1980 (Box 2)
        - U.S. Employees' Retirement Trust, 1979 July 13 (Box 2)
  - Photographs and Negatives
    - Awards reception, undated (negative and photographic enlargement) (Box 2)
    - Television Commercial, 1st Place Winner: Burger King,(Metter at podium), undated (Box 2)
  - Professional biography
    - Career biography, circa early 1980s (Box 2)
    - JWT promotions
      - Promotion to Vice President: New York Times photo/blurb, 1966 (Box 2)
      - Promotion to Executive Vice President: Graphics article, circa 1978 (Box 2)
      - Promotion to Executive Creative Director (press/memos), 1982 (Box 2)
      - Promotion to Vice Chairman JWT (press/radio), 1984 (Box 2)
  - Ross Roy Advertising
    - Automotive advertising brochure, circa 1980s (Box 2)
- Writings Series, 1953-1989 and undated, 4 boxes
  Contains writings by Metter on the advertising industry, along with and one speech by JWT executive Burt Manning. Bulk of series is composed of drafts and research for an unpublished book manuscript, working title Breaking the Rules at J. Walter Thompson, an account of JWT's transformations throughout the late 1970s and 1980s. Of particular research value are several folders of sources for Chapter 2 of this manuscript (reports outlining the history of JWT; a New York Times article announcing the original JWT donation to Duke University) and chapter drafts/press clippings documenting the WPP takeover of JWT in 1987. Book manuscript arranged by chapter, therein alphabetically.
  - Article: Clio and Beyond, Backstage, 1982 June 18 (Box 2)
  - Book manuscript: Breaking the Rules at J. Walter Thompson
    - Chapter drafts
      - Introduction: The Idea and Chapter 1: Shot Out of a Cannon, Notes and research, undated (Box 2)
      - Chapter 2: The University of Advertising
        - Draft, undated (Box 2)
        - Notes, undated (Box 2)
        - Sources
          - A 5-Minute History of the World's Most Experienced Advertising Agency, 1983 (Box 2)
          - J. Walter Thompson Company(23-page article in unidentified magazine/journal), circa 1947 (Box 2)
          - J. Walter Thompson News: The Resor Years, 1984 Feb. (Box 2)
            (Stanley Resor was the CEO of JWT from 1916 until he retired in 1961.)
          - Madison Avenue: JWT: A New Approach to Creativity, 1966 Sept. (Box 2)
            See page 24.
          - Madison Avenue, U.S.A.: How To Run A Great Big Agency: Mostly J. Walter Thompson, 1957 (Box 2)
            Photocopied chapter from published book. Metter's notes in margin indicate this book was a best seller published in 1957.
          - The Many Worlds of Meek: A Legacy of Leadership (published by JWT), 1981 (Box 2)
          - New York Times: J. Walter Thompson Donates Its Archives (Advertising column by Philip H. Dougherty), 1987 Dec. 1 (Box 2)
            Blurb on the original donation of JWT archives to Duke University.
          - Some Basic Roots of the J. Walter Thompson Company: A Starting Point for Future Growth, Howard Henderson, 1953 and 1959 Nov. (Box 2)
      - Chapter 3: Least Likely to Succeed (Box 3)
        - Draft, undated (Box 3)
        - Notes and sources, 1956, 1959 and undated (Box 3)
      - Chapter 4: The Iacocca Years
        - Drafts, undated (Box 3)
        - Notes and clippings, 1967-1988 and undated (Box 3)
        - Sources
          - J. Walter Thompson Company News, 1969 June 2 (Box 3)
          - Notes from 1971 Advance Advertising Planning Meeting, 1969 July (Box 3)
          - Pinto: 1971 Ford TV Commercial: video/audio script, 1970 June 1 (Box 3)
          - Review of 1971 Competitive Introductory Advertising presentation report, 1970 Oct. 26 (Box 3)
        - Subchapters
          - 4A: First Blood
            - Draft, undated (Box 3)
            - Notes and sources, undated (Box 3)
          - 4B: The Fixer
            Alternate chapter titles: The Me and Only and Mr. Fixit.
            - Draft, undated (Box 3)
            - Notes and sources, 1971-1975 and undated (Box 3)
          - 4C: The Small Cans and the Whopper, undated (Box 3)
      - Chapter 5: Scandal (Ford, 1978)
        - Draft, undated (Box 3)
        - Sources
          - Madison Avenue: Industry Feature: Imported Car Advertising issue, 1978 Jan. (Box 3)
          - Various, 1978-1988 and undated (Box 3)
        - Subchapters
          - 5A: The Golden Boy and the Kamikaze Kid: draft, undated (Box 3)
          - 5B: Thompson Reborn: draft/sources, 1979-1980 and undated (Box 3)
      - Chapter 6: Scandal Again (December 1982)
        - Draft, undated (Box 3)
        - Research (notes, clippings), 1976, 1982-1988 and undated (Box 3)
      - Chapter 7: Turnaround
        - Draft, undated (Box 3)
        - Research (notes, clippings), 1983-1984 and undated (Box 3)
        - Sources, 1983-1987 and undated (Box 3)
      - Chapter 8: Succession Obsession, research, 1986-1987 and undated (Box 3)
      - Chapter 9: The Not So Obvious Choice, 1985, 1987 and undated (Box 3)
      - Chapter 10: Fallout (August 1986), 1986 and undated (Box 3)
      - Chapter 11: Conflict, 1986-1988 and undated (Box 4)
      - Chapter 12: The Plot (December 1986), 1987 and undated (Box 4)
      - Chapter 13: Explosion (January 1987), 1983-1988 and undated (Box 4)
      - Chapter 14: Picking Up the Pieces (February/March 1987), 1986-1987 and undated (Box 4)
        Includes Directors Report on Coverage of Events, February 1987.
      - Chapter 15: I Want Your Job/ Shot Out Of A Cannon (April 1987), 1986-1987 and undated (Box 4)
        Includes clippings and memoranda on Metter's resignation from JWT.
      - Chapter 16: Capt. Queequeg (May/June 1987), 1987-1988 and undated (Box 4)
        Contains Harvard Business Review issue, including essay The Dark Side of CEO Succession, by Manfred F.R. Kets De Vries.
      - Chapter 17: In Play (June/July 1987), 1987-1988 and undated (Box 4)
      - Chapter 18: The Battle (June 1987), research and clippings, 1987-1988 and undated (Box 4)
        Includes news clippings on the WPP takeover of JWT.
      - Chapter 19: Full Circle, 1986-1988 and undated (Box 4)
      - Chapter 20: Tomorrow, research notes and clippings, 1987-1989 and undated (Box 4)
    - The Cast (JWT executives), 1987-1988 and undated (Box 4)
      Contains materials on JWT executives Don Johnston, Jack Peters, and Burt Manning, among others.
    - Chapter outline, undated (Box 4)
    - Interviews, 1987-1988 and undated (Box 4)
    - Manuscript draft (typed with editorial notes), undated (Box 4)
    - Research materials (notes, clippings) (Box 5)
      - Duke Special Collections Library (RBMSCL) research: photocopies and notes, 1943-1988 and undated, 2 folders (Box 5)
        Includes original correspondence with Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library, Duke University, related to manuscript research and original 1987 JWT donation.